hi this is Eric Weinstein thanks for
coming back to my youtube channel it's
been a little while since I posted that
first video asking for suggestions what
content I might try to put out and I've
gotten a lot of great feedback so I've
been looking at your comments and been
thinking about what videos might be the
most interesting
I thought however I should start first
with a question of why the intellectual
dark web has such a crazy name so I
believe that I'm guilty I introduced the
phrase intellectual dark web on stage at
the Masonic theatre with ben shapiro and
sam harris and then sam titled that
episode of his podcast the intellectual
dark web and that was later amplified by
barry weiss and others on Barry's
article the new york times particularly
about a lot of play so a lot of people
have asked why does this why does this
movement have such a strange and crazy
name and i thought i would talk a little
bit about the thinking that went into it
given that the first wave of reactions i
think has really started to peter out so
there's still some a few fresh takes but
for the most part the big players have
already commented and I wanted to let
that time pass before I clarified it
further alright so there's a little bit
of design behind the name the central
thesis is that what is now called the
commentariat was always going to hate
both the emergent phenomenon of the
movement and hate any name that we
attach to it why is that is it because
the ideas are terrible is it because the
people involved in the movement are
deplorable I don't think so it's
specifically because what the
intellectual dark web actually is is an
alternative sense making collective so
in this case these so-called IDW will
take what is ever happening in the world
and will try to analyze it but very
often it sounds very different than what
you see in typical mainstream
publications particularly those that we
on the left and depended upon for
curating the interpretations of what is
happening in the world so whether that's
the Atlantic or national public radio or
the New York Times these organizations
have
recently behave quite differently than
many of us remember them let's say 20
years ago the so called commentary at
that is the people who regularly give
their takes on what's happening in the
world seem to have been somewhat
captured by a new network which thinks
in terms that are very different to the
networks that have previously lived at
these organizations and as a result I
believe that the intellectual dark web
is going to be perceived as rivals and
then therefore instead of the
commentariat giving an accurate
assessment of what we're doing they're
going to view us as a rival to their
business model and they're going to
attack on those two on those terms
therefore because of their power and
influence which while waning is still
considerable we always knew that
whatever name this this phenomenon had
it was always going to be beaten up by
the commentary so what we decided or
least what I decided in introducing the
name was to use what I call a Nesta
fadjen strategy now that word I guess is
Portuguese and it comes from the process
that produces the wine named Madeira and
Madeira is really distinguished because
it's the only one that I know that when
you open it up you can leave it open and
it doesn't go bad it doesn't behave like
a normal agricultural product why is
that because it's been subjected to
heating an oxidization in the process
called as the Faja
therefore the product is more sort of
born to use in the same Talib's phrase
in an anti fragile state that was the
idea behind naming this movement the
intellectual dark web or IDW as a result
because it's got such a crazy and some
people would say cringe-worthy or
disturbing or self-important name it's
hard to beat up on it further than it
already has been beaten up on at birth
so from inception it's a very easy thing
to make fun of that guaranteed that we
would have high mimetic acceptance that
is the commentariat actually in some
sense loves the name and so they would
spread it so if you like it's also a bit
of a Trojan horse strategy and that's
what they did
they spread this name far and wide
making fun of it as much as they could
and the fun part about it is that there
are a couple of jokes in the name which
I will now explain since I think that
they've kind of out outlived their
usefulness as jokes the first one is on
the word dark
now the word dark has two basic
interpretations here the first
interpretation is something that's hard
to find so if you go dark it means that
you're sort of in stealth mode now we
have not really been in stealth mode as
many people have pointed out for example
paul krugman my policy under now why is
that funny well it's funny because the
only people to whom we've been dark have
been the mainstream media which had not
wanted to talk about a rival
sense-making network so in essence
you've seen very few opportunities to
engage with these ideas at the main
media institutions that have
traditionally been behind the discussion
of intellectual matters in the United
States and elsewhere at least in the
Anglophone world so part of it is a joke
on the media which is that they don't
want particularly to feature us as
responsible and interesting commentators
on events they instead prefer to either
treat us as strange and controversial
figures like controversial professor
Jordan Peterson or far-right activist
Ben Shapiro or noted Islam critic Sam
Harris now in so doing what they're
doing is they're setting you up with the
idea that these people hold ideas that
are perhaps not savory not acceptable
and that gets to the second issue going
on with the word dark the other notion
of dark here is evil or morally bankrupt
and that's part of the joke too because
I don't think that this network is full
of people who are morally bankrupt quite
the contrary
I think it's a group of people looking
for a more decent notion of politics a
more decent notion of
intellectualization so in essence
we are neither dark in this in the sense
that we're hard to find nor will be dark
in the sense that we're pushing for
something terribly disturbing and as a
result when the news media tried to
figure out what we were they
fundamentally were of two minds about it
so one would be that we are dark because
we shouldn't be listened to and
therefore we can't be platformed or this
is ridiculous don't you realize that
these people have wild followings and
huge audiences so you can't really
easily make both arguments on by the
same token if you think about the notion
of dark as in evil one of the arguments
is that we're self-important and
claiming that we have such dangerous
ideas when in fact everything we talked
about is totally banal and uninteresting
that's one way of attacking us and the
other way of attacking us of course is
to say that what we're talking about has
to be D platform because these are the
discarded ideas of a backward past as
far as the the intellectual aspect well
look you know you can always make the
argument that people who are behaving in
an intellectual space are not
intellectuals but there's no shortage of
PhDs in this network I don't think that
people are listening for three hours
stretches to programs that aren't
stimulating their minds I think what's
going on is that this network is
fundamentally simply trying to point out
that another network has arisen and
because that other network lives inside
of the major media institutions of
yesteryear we don't really recognize how
radical the shift in perspective has
been over the last let's say well
particularly the last five years over
the last five or perhaps ten years the
shift inside of places like CNN and like
the New York Times has been dramatic it
is now not possible to cover stories
that go counter narrative to the
narratives held at a place like the New
York Times so for example when my
brother Brett Weinstein is campus that
Evergreen State College
started to experience something that at
least from the outside looks
indistinguishable from it a Maoist
takeover according to the videos the New
York Times - over three weeks in their
news division to cover the story despite
the fact that there had been two opinion
pieces written on this very strange
breakdown in civil society at Evergreen
State why was that why could a story
that was exciting and interesting not be
covered well in fact what was going
wrong was is that it was a
counter-narrative nightmare it was a
story of an eruption of racism but
racism held by blacks on the campus
Naumann by whites and the anti-racists
were white and not black
therefore the story couldn't actually be
reported and therefore there was a three
and a half week gap between when the
story unfolded and when they finally
wrote a first terrible news piece even
after two opinion pieces had already
been written so this is what's happening
from our perspective is that there are
suddenly all sorts of stories that can't
be reported honestly because they go
counter narrative to this new network
that has taken over the major
institutions that we previously rely
upon particularly on the center-left
so that's NPR CNN New York Times and
magazines like the Atlantic now if you
wanted to understand what's really
motivating the intellectual dark web why
do you have a collection of people that
really doesn't have a particular view
doesn't have a common religion or a
common ethnic group it doesn't have a
common political ideology I believe
what's animating us is the complete
disappearance of a previous consensus
around the idea that enlightenment
values should be used to adjudicate
rival sense-making interpretations that
is when you have two interpretations of
what is going on
do you go back to data do you try to
relate it to other theory do you attempt
to ask thought experiments in order to
try to figure out which is the most
reliable interpretation or do you rely
on a rival system that we're only coming
to understand based around personal
destruction so as far as we can tell in
the new system the new network that has
invaded the previous mainstream media
organs is very focused on reputational
destruction of people who offer rival
sense-making
that is if somebody suggests for example
that oh let's take online chests well
world World Chess standings I believe
have the top hundred chess players only
one of them is female now I have no idea
why that is but I can come up with
buckets I can say well some amount of
this is cultural some amount of this is
systemic bias some of this is biology
some amount of this is socialization but
whatever is going on it's very unlikely
that the right way to begin such a
discussion is to assume that the
representation must be 50/50 if it's
fair and that any deviation from 50/50
generally has to represent some kind of
structural bias against one group by
another the fact that we can't have that
conversation is not particularly
important in the world of chest
who cares about chess nobody cares about
chess I think what's frightening to
people is the idea that you can't ask
the question might this have something
to do with biological differences I mean
99 to 1 it just doesn't make sense to
exclude that and settle on an oppression
narrative from the get-go so because
that example doesn't really matter much
to anyone because chess isn't
determining the fate of the world it's
sort of a clean
to ask the question of why we should be
listening to a group of people that
doesn't seem capable of setting up a
scientific hypothesis and testing it I
would say that what the network what
characterizes the network that has taken
over our mainstream organs is that it is
intrinsically hostile to the idea of
investigating its claims and this is
very much what happened for example to
my brother I don't think people
understood that but there was a lot of
hostility because he used words like
genotype and phenotype as a biologist
which the activists at Evergreen State
took to be evidence that he was clearly
a racist which I'm sorry to say is one
of the stupidest things I've ever heard
in my life if I hadn't seen it on video
I would not believe that people were
capable of making that argument it's
just a shock and the fact that that that
style of argumentation has spread so
quickly and it's penetrated the organs
that we have always depended upon and
have a very long and storied history I
think is probably what animates the
intellectual dark web so dekappa to wrap
up the the reasons for the name the idea
was we wanted to create a name that was
highly mimetic we knew it was going to
be beaten up on we wanted it to be born
anti fragile and we wanted it also to be
understandable as an emergent phenomenon
so you know whether or not I named it it
was always going to be a thing if you
come to any of the shows that we do in
different cities if you watch the view
counts even when the platforms like
YouTube and Twitter seems to me not make
our lives easy this has tremendous
traction people are incredibly excited
about finding that there is some place
to discuss ideas again and furthermore
that we can do so decently without you
know in general resorting to epithet and
reputational destruction unless somebody
else usually initiates hostility towards
us I think it's an incredibly hopeful
movement
and I want to say more about it in
future videos as to what it what really
characterizes the movement what its
interests are but I wanted to begin by
letting you know that the crazy name is
not an accident it's really born out of
a frustration that we know that we're
going up against the people that you
usually have depended upon to curate
your world and its interpretations and
what we are is a rival curation Network
and we don't agree with each other I
mean you know one of the funny things
about it is that we're frequently told
that we are a right-of-center
organization where if I have to be
honest when I sit inside the network I
definitely think it has a left-of-centre
bias and the fact that the left is so
far gone that it sees that as right of
center I think you know speaks volumes I
think about oh I don't know Joe Rogan
Brett Weinstein myself
Sam Harris Heather huiying there's no
shortage of people on the left and I
would definitely say that the movement
is in general not particularly friendly
to the current administration sitting
inside of the White House and the fact
that it can't be understood or or
reported to be what it actually is is in
part what we wanted to show you we want
to show you the failure of the comment
area and I think that until you see this
layer which prefers to be almost
invisible by by virtue of making itself
nearly I don't know well maybe it's
translucent you can sort of see it a
little bit but they really want you to
focus on their interpretation of the
facts rather than the facts themselves
and by calling too much attention to
themselves that goes away I think what
we what we're trying to do is to
highlight that the curation is almost at
the level of a Potemkin village you're
being shown very limited perspectives
and you're seeing a lot of variation
around these perspectives but maybe the
real action is a million miles away from
the sort of center of mass as determined
by the left and right wing comment
as we now understand so I think with the
intellectual dark Weber IDW is going to
do is going to move that considerably
the move the folk the fossa and left and
right considerably off of where the
normal media institutions have been
discussing matters particularly on
matters like trade immigration terror
and and let's say workplace opportunity
so I hope you'll get excited about this
you'll start to see the humor in it
because we throw out a MacGuffin and
sure enough the commentary at everybody
in the comment area saw exactly what it
was that they wanted to see maybe we
were an anti-semitic Network maybe we
were an overly Jewish Network some
people saw us as being almost
exclusively male some people saw this as
an ethnic network all of these things
are just not true and that's what's
funny it's amusing we hope you're in on
the joke now and we hope that
furthermore it's not a terrible name
once you get used to it so get excited
there's more to come and thanks for
watching and greetings from the IDW be
well